So this was the aftermath of his training, huh?
原來這是他修行造成的痕跡
ORIGINAL STORY BY KANEHITO YAMADA / TSUKASA ABE
（原作：山田鐘人，作畫：阿部司）
You aren't going to fight the dragon, right?
你不是不打算跟龍打嗎？
Then why continue your training?
那為什麼還要繼續修行？
When I came to this village,
我剛來到這個村子時
everyone looked dreary, and they were terrified of the dragon.
大家看起來都很陰鬱，而且非常怕龍
But now, those same people are laughing happily.
但現在那些人都能開心地笑著
They say, "This village is safe because Master Stark is here."
說什麼因為有修塔爾克大人在 所以村子現在很安全
Even though I haven't done anything.
明明我什麼都沒做
The only reason the dragon hasn't attacked
龍之所以沒有攻擊這裡
is because it's not in the mood.
也只是因為牠目前沒有那個心情而已
If the dragon attacks the village,
如果龍攻擊這個村子的話
will you fight?
你會戰鬥嗎？
I'd rather die. But you know…
我寧可去死還比較好，但是…
to the people of this village, I am a hero.
對這個村子裡的人而言，我是英雄啊
I'm Stark, the hero of the village.
我是這個村子的英雄，修塔爾克
I have to be the one who protects it.
那麼我就非得保護村子不可
That being said,
雖然話是這麼說
I might run away when the time actually comes.
到時候我說不定會落跑呢
Even this scar on my forehead
就連我額頭上這個傷
is from an argument I had with my master
也是跟師父吵架留下的
over not wanting to fight monsters.
因為我不想跟魔物戰鬥
That was the first time he ever hit me.
那是他第一次出手打我
I'm sure I disappointed him.
我想他一定對我很失望
In the end,
直到最後
my master didn't praise me even once.
我師父一次都沒有誇過我
What?
幹什麼？
Master Stark,
修塔爾克大人
I don't think you will run.
我覺得你不會臨陣脫逃
-What do you know about me? -I don't know a thing.
-妳知道我什麼了？ -我什麼都不知道
But I remembered how scared I was.
但我記得我以前遇過可怕的事
Scared?
可怕的事？
The first time I fought a monster.
我第一次面對魔物時
I had gone through
明明已經接受過
more than enough training up until then.
非常充分的訓練
But I became weak in the knees out of fear,
卻依舊克服不了恐懼
and I ran away.
轉身就逃
The monster kept chasing me.
魔物不斷追趕我
And for some reason Mistress Frieren would not help me.
不知道為什麼，芙莉蓮大人不來救我
Oh, that's how my master is too.
我師父也是這樣
In the end, when it caught up to me,
最後，我被逼得走投無路了
I strengthened my resolve
下定決心的那一刻
and my body moved.
身體就自己動了起來
All I needed was resolve.
我需要的不過是決心而已
Everything you've acquired up until now will not betray you.
你至今為止所累積的一切不會背叛你
You may be a hopeless coward,
也許你是個無可救藥的膽小鬼
but I am sure that your resolve
但我相信你那份
to protect the village is genuine.
想保護村子的決心是真的
Resolve, huh?
決心嗎？
How was it?
怎麼樣？
I don't know.
不知道呢
I don't know,
雖然我不知道
but I'm sure it'll be all right.
但我相信一切會沒問題的
He's not here. He ran, huh?
他沒來，是逃跑了吧？
And I had high hopes for him too.
虧我對他期望還那麼高
Oh well.
沒辦法
Fern, it's time to play tag with the dragon.
費倫，跟龍玩鬼抓人吧
What?
什麼？
Frieren.
芙莉蓮
You need me to buy you 30 seconds, right?
只要爭取到三十秒就好，對吧？
You're late.
你也太慢了
Can you promise me one thing?
能答應我一件事嗎？
Even if I die in the middle of it,
萬一我在戰鬥時喪命
will you make sure to kill the dragon?
一定要殺掉那條龍
Okay, I promise.
好，我答應你
But why are you going this far just for the villagers?
不過你為什麼 要為村民做到這種地步？
What?
怎麼了？
Oh, I just thought it was a strange question.
我只是覺得這個問題很奇怪
I've been in this village for three whole years.
我在這個村裡待了整整三年
-Not very long, huh? -It's very long.
-很短啊 -超長的吧
All right, let's get this done!
好，那就動手吧！
-Your hands are shaking. -It's scary, okay?
-你的手在發抖 -會怕就是會怕啊
You don't have to laugh.
沒必要笑我吧
You're just like Eisen.
你跟艾冉真像
My master?
師父？
We've got ourselves a strong opponent.
這次的對手很強
Eisen, your hands are shaking. Are you scared?
艾冉，你的手在發抖，你怕了嗎？
Yeah.
是啊
You admit it so quickly.
承認得還真乾脆
Feeling scared is not a bad thing.
感到恐懼並不是壞事
This fear
是這份恐懼
is what got me this far.
支撐我走到今天
You guys even tremble the same way.
連發抖的方式也一樣呢
I see…
這樣啊
So Master
所以師父…
was also scared.
也會感到害怕
All I need
我需要的…
is my resolve.
只是下定決心而已
He's within the dragon's reach.
他進入龍的攻擊範圍了
It's not attacking yet.
牠還沒出手
It's acting cautious.
龍很戒備他
So I was right…
果然是這樣
No wonder the village was never attacked again.
難怪牠再也沒去攻擊村子
Dragons are smart animals.
龍是很聰明的生物
They aren't foolish enough to willingly pick a fight with a strong opponent.
不會蠢到去找強勁的對手打架
The reason why Eisen hit Stark
艾冉之所以會出手打修塔爾克
was not because Stark was weak
並不是因為修塔爾克很弱
or because Stark disappointed him.
或是因為修塔爾克讓他失望了
We had a fight and parted ways.
我們吵了一架就分開了
You hit him?
你打了他？
My body reacted by reflex.
身體不由自主就動了起來
I feel bad for what I did.
我做了一件很糟的事
I was scared.
但我當時很害怕
I was scared, Frieren.
我很害怕，芙莉蓮
He truly is an amazing guy.
他真的是很厲害的傢伙
My apprentice
我的徒弟…
will become an incredible warrior.
會成為不得了的戰士
Okay! Shoot it now!
就是現在，立刻動手！
Come on! Why aren't you shooting?
搞什麼！為什麼還不動手？
I did everything you asked!
我都照妳說的做了！
You're making me fight alone?
難道妳要我一個人打嗎？
Don't you dare, you stinking hag!
別開玩笑了，臭老太婆！
-You're just like Master-- -It's already dead.
-妳果然也跟師父一樣… -已經死了
Huh?
什麼？
"Stinking hag," huh?
“臭老太婆”嗎？
That's not going to end well.
看來之後會很不妙啊
Did I
是我…
do it?
幹掉的？
I killed a dragon
我自己一個人…
on my own?
就打敗龍了？
Stark,
修塔爾克
good job.
做得好
You exceeded my expectations. Well done.
比我預期的還要好呢，不錯嘛
A mountain of treasures!
滿坑滿谷的寶山啊！
We can't take all of that.
不可以全拿喔
You're only allowed three.
只可以拿三個
It really is nonsensical.
真的是很無聊呢
How can you become engrossed in this?
妳怎麼會這麼熱衷於這種東西？
It's a mountain of treasures.
這可是座寶山
Master said that the adventure
師父說過，勇者一行人的冒險
of the party of heroes was completely nonsensical because of you.
因為妳變得好無聊
Yeah?
是嗎？
He said it was
他說
a nonsensical yet extremely fun journey.
那是個很無聊，卻非常好玩的旅行
Wow! Shaved ice is really coming out!
好厲害，真的跑出刨冰了！
Wasn't it worth the search?
不枉之前那麼費力地找它了吧？
And this is the fluffy kind, not the crunchy kind!
而且還鬆鬆軟軟的 不是脆脆的那種！
You're right!
真的耶！
What nonsense.
真是無聊
Are you okay with this?
做這種事沒關係嗎？
What's the harm?
無傷大雅吧？
Our journey has just begun.
我們的旅途才剛剛開始
Even the Hero of the South, who is known as the strongest of mankind,
就連譽為最強人類的南方勇者
was killed by the Demon King's Seven Sages of Destruction.
都被魔王麾下的七崩賢殺掉了
We don't know if we can return alive either.
我們自己也不知道能不能活著回去
Eisen, do you want to go on a difficult and painful journey?
艾冉，你是想要一場 艱難又痛苦的旅行嗎？
You know,
我啊
I want to go on a fun journey that we can call nonsensical
我想要一場有趣的旅行 那種在結束之後
and laugh about once it's done.
能夠笑著說：“真是很無聊”的旅行
Look at this!
妳看這個！
It melts the moment you touch it.
摸到的瞬間就融化了
-Don't touch it. It's food. -Nonsense…
-不要摸，那是吃的 -無聊…
By the way, where's the syrup?
對了，芙莉蓮，糖漿呢？
I don't have a spell that produces syrup.
我沒有可以變出糖漿的魔法
-You don't? -This is seriously nonsensical.
-妳沒有？ -真的是很無聊耶
How is it? Can you see through it?
怎麼樣？能看透嗎？
I can see.
可以
But it's not a very interesting spell.
不過這個魔法不怎麼有趣耶
Well, I'm sorry my body isn't interesting.
還真抱歉喔，我的身材不怎麼有趣
What?
幹嘛？
-So small… -It's not small!
-好小… -才不小好不好！
Well then, what are you going to do now, Stark?
那你現在打算怎麼辦，修塔爾克？
You can return to Eisen's place too.
你也可以回去艾冉家
Master told you to take me along, right?
師父要妳帶著我去吧？
Plus,
而且
I want to go on
我也想要…
a nonsensical journey too.
來場無聊的旅行了
28 YEARS FROM THE DEATH OF HIMMEL THE HERO
（勇者欣梅爾逝世的28年後）
RIEGEL CANYON IN THE CENTRAL LANDS FORTRESS CITY, WAAL
（中央諸國 里格爾峽谷，要塞城市瓦爾）
The monsters are very active in the northern lands.
由於北方諸國的魔物活動很頻繁
Currently, we are not allowing anyone through the checkpoint.
目前關口不開放通行
When will the checkpoint open up again?
那關口什麼時候會開放呢？
Who knows?
天知道
For as long as I've been assigned here,
至少從我受命待在這裡開始
I have not allowed a single monster or man through.
任何魔物或人類，我都不曾放行
Excuse me.
打擾一下
Captain, the castellan is asking for you.
隊長，城代大人請您過去
I'll be there.
我馬上過去
Got that, adventurers?
聽懂了嗎，冒險者？
Make sure that you don't cause any trouble in this city.
不要給鎮上帶來麻煩
That wasn't a very nice welcome.
沒給我們好臉色看呢
Yeah. He is a very capable guard.
是啊，那是很優秀的衛兵
Being strict to outsiders
對外來者態度嚴謹
is how a true guard who protects the citizens should act.
保護民眾的衛兵就應該這樣
And so…
話說回來…
This city seems safe,
這座城鎮看來很安全
so let's wait it out here.
所以我們就在這裡等待吧
I can finally take my time and study magic again.
我終於又可以悠哉地研究魔法了
I'll drop my luggage off at the inn and go to the magic store.
我先去旅店寄放行李 然後就去魔法商店
What?
怎麼了？
The checkpoint isn't open, so we have no choice.
關口不開放，那也無可奈何啊
All right, we'll split up here.
好，我們就在這裡解散吧
I'll go book an inn.
我去訂旅店
Want to go get food?
要不要去吃飯？
Never mind, I'll go by myself.
不用介意，我自己去
So scary…
好可怕…
I heard you can't even go by sea these days.
我聽說最近連海路都不能走
They say an army from the northern lands is being deployed,
據說北方諸國部屬了軍隊
but it'll take at least two years for the checkpoint to reopen.
關口起碼要兩年才會開放
It's terrible for businesses.
生意都做不了了
This brings back memories.
真令人懷念啊
The Jumbo Berry Special.
超大莓果特製聖代
The last time I came here, I was a kid
上次來這裡的時候，我還是個小孩
so I couldn't eat it all and I shared it with Master.
因為一個人吃不完 跟師父一起分著吃
But was it this small?
不過之前有這麼小嗎？
You feel that way because you've become an adult.
那是因為你已經是個大人了
I see.
這樣啊
I'm the one who grew, huh?
長大的人是我啊
Everything seemed so big when I was a kid.
小時候不管什麼看起來都很大
But even Master's broad shoulders
就連師父寬闊的肩膀
started looking small after a while.
不知何時看起來也變小了
Eisen is up in years now.
艾冉先生年紀大了
You better be a good son to him.
你要好好孝順他
I'm trying to right now.
我正在努力呢
But really, was it always this small?
但當時真的有這麼小嗎？
The passage of time is very harsh, isn't it?
歲月的流逝還真是毫不留情呢
What? Don't judge me.
幹嘛啦？有什麼關係？
I bought it with my own money.
我用我自己的錢買的
Excuse me, can I have milk please?
不好意思，請給我杯牛奶
Coming up.
馬上來
Uh, what?
呃，怎麼了？
Why are you mad?
妳幹嘛生氣？
Master Stark…
修塔爾克大人…
Fine, I'll give you half.
知道了啦，分妳一半可以吧
That's not what I want.
問題不是那個
If I told you that we might have to stay here for over two years,
如果說我們要在這裡待超過兩年
how would you feel?
你怎麼想？
Huh? I'd hate that.
什麼？當然不想啊
-Right? You'd hate that, right? -Yeah…
-是吧？你不想吧？ -對啊…
What's wrong with her?
這個人是怎麼了？
I'm so relieved.
我安心了
So you are normal after all.
你也是個正常人呢
Hey, did I do something wrong?
是說，我有做錯什麼嗎？
A way to pass through the checkpoint, huh?
穿過關口的方法嗎？
Sure, I'll help you find one.
好，我幫妳想辦法
Thank you.
謝謝
We can't just jump and fly over it?
不能直接跳上城牆飛過去嗎？
You can't cross the border facing
北方諸國邊境和上空
the northern lands because of a powerful barrier that stretches
設有強大的結界
up to its highest possible limit.
所以無法通過
That makes sense.
那就說得通了
Otherwise, it'd be open to monsters who can fly.
不然會飛的魔物就能通過了
That can't be helped. Let's check the merchants guild.
那就沒辦法了，去商人行會問問吧
It might be open for trade at least.
至少應該會開放通商
Trade has been completely blocked.
商貿完全中止了
They won't even allow guarded caravans.
連雇用護衛的商隊都不能放行
The northern lands must be pretty dangerous.
看來北方諸國現在一定相當危險
I guess we'll have to wait until things settle down.
看來只能坐等情勢穩定了
No.
不
Let's try the black market and thieves' guild.
去問問黑市跟盜賊行會吧
Isn't that too dangerous?
那不是很危險嗎？
Don't worry. I come across pretty strong.
不用擔心，我看起來可是很強的
And I'm good at faking it.
而且我也很會裝裝樣子
-You do have a villain's face. -Shut up.
-你確實長了張壞人臉呢 -閉嘴啦
No success, huh?
不行啊
I guess it's to be expected.
想想也是
This is basically a defensive war.
基本上這已經是防衛戰狀態了
You can't do anything unless the gate opens.
除非關口開放，不然什麼都做不了
All right.
好吧
Next, let's try the guard station just in case.
接下來姑且就去衛兵站問問看吧
-What? -Nothing…
-幹嘛？ -沒什麼…
I'm just surprised at how cooperative you are.
我只是很意外你那麼配合
You're the one who brought it up.
先開口的人是妳啊
You didn't want to wait, right?
不是不想一直等嗎？
You look more desperate than me.
你看起來比我還要迫切呢
Well, I don't have much time after all.
是啊，畢竟時間也不多了
What do you mean?
什麼意思？
This is a nice view, isn't it?
這裡的景色真美，是吧？
You can see the northern lands.
可以看到北方諸國
When I was small, Master brought me here.
小時候，師父帶我來過這裡
We departed from this city
我們從這座城鎮出發
and headed to the northern lands.
前往北方諸國
What kind of journey was it, Master?
師父，那是什麼樣的旅行？
You want to know?
你想知道？
At the time, we…
那時候，我們…
He never talked about himself at all,
他平常從來不提自己的事
but he eagerly talked about the adventures of the party of heroes.
但談起勇者一行人的冒險卻津津樂道
He treasured that adventure more than anything
他把那場冒險看得比什麼都重要
even though it only accounted for ten years of his long life.
就算那在他漫長的生命裡只佔了十年
I'm sure Frieren is the same way.
我相信芙莉蓮也是一樣的
I don't know…
不知道呢
Master is too old to travel now.
師父年紀大了，不能旅行了
But he told you two to take me along with you.
但他卻要妳們帶我一起走
That's why I'm going to experience
所以我才要代替他
a nonsensical yet fun journey in his place
來場無聊又好玩的旅行
and bring back stories to share with him.
然後帶一堆故事回去講給他聽
This is about the only way I can repay him.
這是我唯一能回報他的方式
If I take too much time, Master is going to die.
如果花太多時間的話，師父會死掉的
Well then, we can't waste time in a place like this.
這樣的話 就更不能在這種地方浪費時間了
But then again, I'll bet he is going to live for a while.
不過啊，師父他 應該還能活上一段時間就是了
Mistress Frieren.
芙莉蓮大人
What are you doing here?
妳在這裡幹嘛？
Shush, be quiet.
噓，別出聲
I'm being chased.
有人在追我
Wh… What did you do?
妳…妳做了什麼事？
I don't know.
不清楚耶
I was only going from one magic store to the next.
我只是一家一家地逛魔法商店
I am terribly sorry!
真的很抱歉！
Mistress Frieren, please forgive me!
芙莉蓮大人，請原諒我！
Wait… I'm getting a very bad feeling…
等等，我有種不好的預感…
It seems the captain of the guards treated you disrespectfully.
看來衛兵隊隊長對您多有冒犯
As the castellan appointed to this city, I apologize.
作為本城的城代，我向您道歉
Uh, it's nothing.
沒關係
He was only doing his job as a guard.
他只是善盡身為衛兵應盡的責任
And I am in no hurry at all.
而且我一點也不趕時間
Actually, I want to--
我反而想悠哉地…
You are going to embark on a journey to the north again, right?
您打算再次啟程前往北方，對吧？
I hear that the northern lands
我聽說北方諸國
are constantly fighting against the remnants of the Demon King's army.
目前仍然持續跟魔王殘黨對戰
I'm sure you are heartbroken by their situation.
相信您一定因為他們的狀況感到憂心
Your willing spirit is indeed that of a hero.
您這樣的胸懷 正是身為英雄應有的情操
I am sure it will delight the people of the northern lands.
相信北方諸國的人民 知道了一定會很高興
Please pass through the checkpoint as you wish.
您可以隨意通過我們的關口
Who knew we could pass through so easily?
竟然這麼簡單就能通過了？
Maybe we should have mentioned your name from the start?
說不定一開始就應該報上您的名號
I thought it would be useless even if I did.
我本來以為就是說了也沒有用
I wanted to take my time…
本來我還打算悠哉地…
And plus, I don't like these kinds of things very much.
而且我並沒有很喜歡這種排場
This view makes me feel uneasy.
這種場面讓人很不自在吧？
I'm glad I got to see this view.
我倒很慶幸可以看到這種場面
Master must have departed for the northern lands like this too.
師父從北方諸國出發時 應該也像現在這樣
Yeah.
是啊
I wanted to study more magic…
我打算多做點魔法研究的…
She's still whining.
還在抱怨
We went through a lot of trouble, you know.
我們可是費了不少功夫耶
-Right? -Yes.
-是吧？ -對啊
-It hurts. -Humans make such a big deal.
-好痛 -人類真是愛小題大作
-Tonight is… -Mother.
-今晚是… -媽媽
…the Liberation Festival.
…解放祭
There is a word.
有一個詞
-I'm interested in that mage. -What a pain.
-我對那個魔法使很感興趣 -真令人頭痛
"Like a Fairy Tale."
童話般的事物
Subtitle translation by: Kiko Morita
字幕翻譯：洪貞韻